Suffrage Collection, 1851-2009 (bulk 1880s-1920s)
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Suffrage collection
1851-2009
1880s-1920s
MS 447
34 boxes, 26 volumes, microforms, and oversize materials (14.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Feminists, Suffragists. Comprised largely of printed materials such as pamphlets, newspaper clippings, petitions, legislative documents, articles, periodicals, and books pertaining to the enfranchisement of women primarily in the U.S., but also in England and there are small amounts of material on other countries. There are also manuscript materials including unpublished writings and correspondence. Photographs document suffrage parades, demonstrations, groups, and individuals. Suffrage memorabilia and ephemera includes broadsides, fliers, cartoons, postcards, buttons, pins, stickers, banners, playing cards, songbooks, a novel, poetry, scrapbooks, and a cookbook. U.S. and British suffrage organizations, such as the National American Woman Suffrage Association, the National Women's Party, and the National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies are well represented; and there are biographical materials, speeches, photographs, and writings by and about prominent suffragists including Carrie Chapman Catt, Jane Addams, Alice Stone Blackwell, Ida Husted Harper, Gertrude Foster Brown, Emmeline Pethick-Lawrence, Emmeline Pankhurst, Anna Howard Shaw, and many others.
The Suffrage Collection documents efforts to gain the vote for women. Although primarily focused on U.S. campaigns, the collection also contains material from the English suffrage movement, and to a lesser extent, women's suffrage in other countries. Types of material include such printed material as pamphlets, leaflets, newspaper and periodical clippings, petitions, legislative documents, and books; manuscript materials including unpublished writings and correspondence; photographs, which document suffrage parades, demonstrations, organizations, and individuals; and suffrage memorabilia and ephemera, including fliers, cartoons, postcards, buttons, pins, stickers, banners, playing cards, songbooks, scrapbooks, and a cookbook.
SERIES I. UNITED STATES is the most comprehensive portion of the collection. The bulk of this series documents the period between the 1880s and 1920s and is divided into eight subseries: Congressional documents, Subjects, Printed materials, Organizations, Individuals, Memorabilia, States, and Anti-Suffrage.
The Congressional documents subseries contains reprints from the Congressional Record and other printed records of bills and arguments regarding women's suffrage presented in the U.S. Senate and House of Representatives arranged chronologically. Materials in the Subjects subseries pertain to particular events and trends in the suffrage movement and consist of clippings, photographs, and pamphlets. Suffrage parades are well represented by the photographs and programs located in this subseries. The Printed materials subseries is arranged by types of material and contains clippings, pamphlets, cartoons, and other publications that encompass the span of the suffrage movement. The Organizations subseries contains significant amounts of printed material and lesser amounts of correspondence and publicity published by national suffrage organizations including the American Woman Suffrage Association, National Woman Suffrage Association, and the College Equal Suffrage League. A large portion of publications and meeting materials, including bound volumes of proceedings and handbooks, represent the National American Woman Suffrage Organization. For state suffrage organizations, see the States subseries.
The Individuals subseries contains limited biographical information and photographs of suffragists. Materials documenting Alice Stone Blackwell, Ida Husted Harper, Gertrude Foster Brown, Alice Park, and Anna Howard Shaw are among the more unique items in this subseries. A whimsical collection of suffrage ephemera can be found in the Memorabilia subseries. Stickers, buttons, playing cards, and sewing accessories advertising "Votes for Women," and photographs of memorabilia, as well as a large collection of pro-suffrage postcards and greeting cards provide a sense of the interplay between political activism and popular culture. Several oversize items, such as a suffrage pennant, veil, and "Votes for Women" tote bag, were removed to the Flat File. The States subseries contains an eclectic mix of materials documenting state-oriented suffrage fights. Many state files contain clippings, publications from local organizations, and histories of state campaigns, while the files for Massachusetts and New York contain more in-depth documentation. A range of materials pertaining to the New York State Woman Suffrage Association, including election tabulations and Suffrage Correspondence School lessons, have been collected, and several Massachusetts state organizations are represented. The final subseries concerns Anti-suffrage activities and includes memorabilia, publications, organizations, and state campaigns in opposition to woman suffrage. Also included is a set of anti-suffrage tracts entitled, Why Women Do Not Want the Ballot.
Note: photographs are interspersed throughout SERIES I. UNITED STATES, especially under Subjects--Parades, and in the Individuals subseries.
SERIES II. ENGLAND documents the English suffrage movement and follows the arrangement of SERIES I. UNITED STATES with the following subseries: Subjects, Printed materials, Organizations, Individuals, and Memorabilia. The bulk of the series dates from the 1890s to the 1910s. The Organizations include publications of the National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies and the St. Joan's Alliance; and files in Individuals contain publications, correspondence, and photographs of the Pankhurst family and Emmeline and Frederick Pethick-Lawrence that document militant resistance to voting restrictions. Researchers interested in English suffrage may also wish to consult the Alice Morgan Wright Papers in the SSC. Wright participated in the militant suffrage campaign of 1912 and was jailed in Holloway Prison.
SERIES III. INTERNATIONAL contains small amounts of material, primarily newspaper clippings, documenting the struggle for women's suffrage in other countries. Files for France, Germany, Denmark, and a few others, contain more diverse types of materials such as publications and photographs.
Oversize materials that were removed from the above series are at the end of the collection and in the Flat File. These include fifteen scrapbooks (1909-20) of Mary Bartlett Dixon Cullen, who collected clippings and printed materials pertaining to suffrage in Maryland and on the national scene; a scrapbook of the Pennsylvania Men's League for Woman Suffrage; posters; newspapers; and memorabilia such as pennants and banners. Over twenty-five volumes of books and suffrage periodicals complete the collection and are listed at the end of this finding aid. A small number of the journals and the fifteen scrapbooks of Mary Cullen are available on microfilm.
This collection is arranged as follows:
SERIES I. UNITED STATES
SERIES II. ENGLAND
SERIES III. INTERNATIONAL
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
BOOKS ON SHELF
MICROFORMS
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additional Formats
Scrapbooks of Mary Bartlett Cullen are available on microfilm. Selected volumes of the Woman's Journal; Jus Suffragii; and Women's Suffrage Pilgrimage Journal are available on microfilm.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this finding aid.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
Blackwell, Alice Stone, 1857-1950--Biography--Sources; Brown, Gertrude Foster, 1867- --Biography--Sources; Harper, Ida Husted, 1851-1931--Biography--Sources; Pankhurst, E. Sylvia (Estelle Sylvia), 1882-1960--Biography--Sources; Pankhurst, Emmeline, 1858-1928--Biography--Sources; Pankhurst, Christabel, Dame, 1880-1958--Biography--Sources; Pethick-Lawrence, Emmeline, 1867- --Biography--Sources; Pethick-Lawrence, Frederick William Pethick Lawrence, Baron, 1871-1961--Biography--Sources; Shaw, Anna Howard, 1847-1919--Biography--Sources; American Woman Suffrage Association--History--Sources; National American Woman Suffrage Association--History--Sources; National Association Opposed to Woman Suffrage--History--Sources; National Woman Suffrage Association (U.S.)--History--Sources; National Woman's Party--History--Sources; Feminism--History-20th century-Sources; Feminism--History-19th century--Sources; Feminists--Biography--Sources; Suffragists--Biography--Sources; United States--Politics and government--1913-1921--Sources; Women--Suffrage--Caricatures and cartoons; Women--Suffrage--Great Britain--History--Sources; Women--Suffrage--Massachusetts--History--Sources; Women--Suffrage--New York (State)--History--Sources; Women--Suffrage--Periodicals; Women--Suffrage--United States--History--Sources; Women--United States--History--Sources; Women's rights--United States--History--Sources; Sophia Smith Collection
Additional Information
Related Material
Researchers should consult the Suffrage Subject Guide (on the SSC Web site) and the card catalog for numerous other sources related to women's suffrage in the Sophia Smith Collection.
- SERIES I. UNITED STATES
  - Congressional documents
    - 1867-79:
      - U.S. House of Representatives. Thomas E. Noell (MO): speech on "Woman Suffrage and Reconstruction of Massachusetts," 1867 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - U.S. Senate. H.C. Ingersoll: petition that the right of suffrage be granted to women in the District of Columbia 1870 (Box 1)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. St. Louis County Woman Suffrage Association: memorial advocating the enfranchisement of women 1871 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on the Judiciary: report on woman suffrage 1872 (Box 1)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. New York Woman Suffrage Society: memorial protesting bill regarding suffrage in Utah 1873 (Box 1)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. New York Woman Suffrage Society: memorial protesting the taxation of women for the Centennial Exhibition 1876 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Privileges and Elections: arguments on behalf of an amendment to the Constitution for the enfranchisement of women 1878-79 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Privileges and Elections: report on a proposed Constitutional amendment to enfranchise women (includes dissenting opinion) 1878-79 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. E.C. Stanton, M.J. Gage, and S.B. Anthony (officers of the National Woman Suffrage Association): memorial requesting an amendment to the Constitution to protect the rights of women citizens 1879 (Box 1)
    - 1880-1883:
      - U.S. House of Representatives. Committee on the Judiciary: arguments on behalf of an amendment to enfranchise women24 Jan 1880 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. Committee on the Judiciary: arguments for woman suffrage (made by members of the Woman Suffrage Convention) 1880 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on the Judiciary: arguments of the Woman-Suffrage delegates23 Jan 1880 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on the Judiciary: arguments of woman suffrage delegatesMar 1880 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: report on a Constitutional amendment to enfranchise women (includes dissenting opinion) 1882 (Box 1)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. Joint resolution proposing an amendment to the Constitution 1882-1883 (Box 1)
    - 1884-87:
      - U.S. House of Representatives. John D. White (KY): speech on the political rights of women7 Feb 1884 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. Tomas B. Reed (ME): dissenting opinion on woman suffrage (minority of the Committee on the Judiciary)24 April 1884 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: report on the proposal of a Constitutional amendment to enfranchise women 1884 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Thomas W. Palmer (MI): speech on universal suffrage6 Feb 1885 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: report on the proposed joint resolution of a Constitutional amendment to enfranchise women 1886 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Henry W. Blair (NH): speech on woman suffrage8 Dec 1886 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Angie F. Newman: petition on woman suffrage by the women of Utah 1886 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Senators H.W. Blair, J.E. Brown, J.N. Dolph, G.G. Vest, and G.F. Hoar: debate on woman suffrage 1886-87 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Reports by the Committee on Woman Suffrage (all in one volume) 1887 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1888-1892:
      - U.S. Senate. International Women's Council: hearing before the Committee on Woman Suffrage2 April 1888 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: report on the joint resolution proposing an amendment to the Constitution for the enfranchisement of women 1889 (Box 1)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. Committee on the Judiciary: report on the resolution proposing an amendment to the Constitution for the enfranchisement of women (Incl. dissenting opinion) 1890 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: petition from the National Woman's Suffrage Association 1892 (Box 1)
    - 1893-96:
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: report on the petition of the National Woman's Suffrage Association of Massachusetts to enfranchise women 1893 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - U.S. Senate. Caroline F. Corbin: memorial against the enfranchisement of women 1893 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: hearing on woman suffrage 1894 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: report on the hearing about the proposal to enfranchise women 1896 (Box 1)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. Committee on the Judiciary: hearing of the National American Woman Suffrage Association on the proposed 16thAmendment 1896 (2 copies) (Box 1)
    - 1898-1902:
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: report on the hearing about the enfranchisement of women 1898 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: hearing on woman suffrage 1900 (Box 1)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. Committee on the Judiciary: hearing on woman suffrage 1902 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: hearing on the proposed Constitutional amendment 1902 (Box 1)
    - 1904-1912:
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: hearing on the proposed Constitutional amendment 1904 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. Committee on the Judiciary: hearing on the proposed Constitutional amendment 1906 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: hearing on the proposed Constitutional amendment, remarks of Belva Lockwood 1906 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. John F. Shafroth (CO): speech before Committee on Woman Suffrage on the enfranchisement of women 1910 (Box 1)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. Committee on the Judiciary: hearing on woman suffrage 1912 (Box 1)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. Edward T. Taylor (CO): speech on equal suffrage in Colorado 1912 (Box 1)
    - 1913-14:
      - U.S. Congress: Congressional Record: petition for woman suffrage in Senate31 July 1913 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: reports and hearings on the proposed amendment 1913 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: report on proposed amendment 1913 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. William E. Borah (ID): speech on local, self-government on the issue of woman suffrage 1914 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: address written by a committee of women of Southern California in favor of the enfranchisement of women 1914 (Box 1)
    - 1915-16:
      - U.S. Senate. James E. Martine (NJ): article on woman suffrage 1915 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. John W. Abercrombie (AL): speech on woman suffrage 1915 (Box 1)
      - U.S. House of Representatives. Frank W. Mondell (WY): extracts from speeches in the House12 Jan l9l5 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: hearings on proposed constitutional amendment 1916 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. Thomas. B.Catron (NM): article on woman suffrage 1916 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Senate. John F. Shafroth (CO): speech on equal suffrage 1916 (Box 1)
    - 1917, 1945:
      - U.S. House of Representatives. Meyer London (NY): speech on woman suffrage 1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - U.S. Senate. Committee on Woman Suffrage: hearing on proposed Constitutional amendment 1917 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Congress. Joint Resolution authorizing Woman's Enfranchisement Day2 Nov l945 (Box 1)
  - Subjects
    - Catholic view of woman suffrage: clippings, leaflets, and pamphlets 1913-23, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - History
      - Historical and retrospective articles (photocopies and originals) 1924-2009, undated, [please use photocopies] (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
      - Fiftieth Anniversary of Woman Suffrage Amendment: clippings and celebration material (primarily from Amherst, MA) 1970 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Parades, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
      - Programs, ephemera, and clippings 1913-1915, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Photographs (photocopies and originals) 1911-1915, undated, [please use photocopies] (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
    - Trade unions and woman suffrage: fliers and clippings 1915-18, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - White House picketing: pamphlets, clippings, correspondence from Alice Paul, and photograph with Theodore Roosevelt 1917-18, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Printed materials
    - Broadsides and leaflets 1872-1919, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Cartoons: photocopies, photographs, and originalsundated, [please use photocopies] (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    - Maps and charts 1912-23, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Newspaper clippings
      - 1889-99 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - 1900-27, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Novel: The Sturdy Oak: A Composite Novel of American Politics by fourteen American authors 1917 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Pamphlets 1858-1919, undated, [see separate title list in folder] (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - Periodicals, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS, and MICROFORMS: Woman's Journal and Jus Suffragii]
      - Articles about woman suffrage from American and British magazines 1869-1919, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Harper's Weekly (special suffrage issue)May 1915; and The Revolution (photo of front page), Jan 1870 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - "The Torch Bearer" by Agnes Ryan (history of the Woman's Journal) 1916 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Poetry (includes William Lloyd Garrison II, C.H. Forbes, and Mira H. Pitman) 1895, 1915, 1920, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Woman Suffrage Leaflet" series and "Equal Suffrage Leaflets" from The Woman's Journal publishers 1891-1904, [see also Organizations--American Woman Suffrage Association] (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Organizations
    - American Woman Suffrage Association: "Woman Suffrage" leaflets and constitution 1881-90, undated (continues as the National American Woman Suffrage Association after 1890), [see also Printed materials, "Woman Suffrage Leaflet" series for post-1890 publications] (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - College Equal Suffrage League: mission statements, newsletters, pamphlets, and "The Woman Suffrage Calendar," 1905-14 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Congressional Union for Woman Suffrage: itineraries, leaflets, speeches, and essays 1916, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Leslie Woman Suffrage Commission: The Record of the Leslie Woman Suffrage Commission, Inc. 1917-1929, by Rose Young, 1929, [see also States--New York] (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Men's League for Woman Suffrage: pamphlets by Max Eastmanundated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - National American Woman Suffrage Association (NAWSA) (continues the American and National Woman Suffrage Associations), [see also BOOKS ON SHELF--Victory: How Women Won It, 1840-1940; Woman Suffrage: Arguments and Results; NAWSA Proceedings and Handbooks, 1893-1920; and OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
      - Constitution 1890 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Meetings
        - Annual convention programs
          - 1893-98 (Box 4, Folder 11-13)
          - 1899-1902, 1906 (includes "College Evening" program); 1915-20; and clippings and minutes from 1925, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
        - Mass meeting at Carnegie Hall: "Votes for Women on the Home Stretch": program 1913 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Publications
        - Fliers 1913-18, n.d (Box 5, Folder 7)
        - Lists of leaflets and pamphlets in box (Box 5, Folder 8)
        - Leaflets 1913-19, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
        - Woman Suffrage Leaflet Series, [see Organizations--American Woman Suffrage Association, and Printed material--Woman Suffrage leaflet series] (Box 5)
        - Pamphlets published by NAWSA
          - A-F 1897-1919, 1942, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
          - G-Z 1897-1919, 1942, undated (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
          - Political Equality Series 1898-1905, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
        - Headquarters Newsletter (incomplete) 1915-17 (Box 6, Folder 4)
        - The Woman Suffrage Yearbook 1917 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - National Suffrage Association: "Declaration and Pledge," 1871 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - National Woman Suffrage and Education Committee: leaflet 1871 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - National Woman Suffrage Association: leaflets, pamphlets, and Report of the Sixteenth Annual Washington Convention ed. by Stanton and Anthony 1881-89 (continues as the National American Woman Suffrage Association after 1890) (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Women's Political Union: invitation, leaflets, book list, and membership card 1915, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Individuals
    - Blackwell, Alice Stone
      - Clippings, tributes, and obituaries 1874, 1925-50 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence 1900-47 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Publications and typescripts 1884-1907, 1919-38, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Photographs (includes Anna Howard Shaw) (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Blair, Ida: photographundated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Blatch, Harriot Stanton: photograph and clipping 1940, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Briggs-Wall, Henrietta: copies of materials from Kansas State Historical Society 1920, 1939, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Brown, Gertrude Foster, [see also States--New York--Your Vote and How to Use It (1918), and BOOKS ON SHELF for Suffrage and Music: My First Eighty Years]
      - Watercolor and photograph 1969, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence 1941-47, 1952, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Notes and research materials for speeches for the Women's Action League for Lasting Peace 1945, 1947, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - "On Account of Sex," manuscriptundated (Box 7, Folder 7-9)
    - Clay, Laura: book, Bitter Harvest: Laura Clay's Suffrage Work 1946 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Cooley, Belle: clipping 1924 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Couzzins, Phoebe, [see OVERSIZE MATERIALS] (Box 8)
    - Cullen, Mary Bartlett Dixon: scrapbooks 1909-20, [see MICROFORMS- m24] (Box 8)
    - Dennett, Mary Ware 1947, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Gannett, Mary Thorn Lewis: clippings 1952 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Gardener, Helen H. (U.S. Civil Service Commissioner): photographundated (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Harper, Ida Husted
      - Publications written by Harper 1907-15, undated, [see also Organizations--NAWSA pamphlets] (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - The International Woman Suffrage News 1918-20 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Clippings about Harper and presidential inauguration invitation 1916-20 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Havemeyer, Loisine W.: pamphlet 1922 (Box 8, Folder 9)